The translation and publication of the
Zohar is made possible through the
thoughtful and generous support of the
Pritzker Family Philanthropic Fund.
The administrative support to this project
in its initial period by the Graduate
Theological Union is gratefully
acknowledged.
Stanford University Press, Stanford,
California 2004 by Zohar Education
Project, Inc. All rights reserved. For
further information, including the Aramaic
text of the Zohar, please visit www. sup.
org/zohar Library of Congress
Cataloging-in-Publication Data for Printed
Edition Zohar. English. The
Zohar/translation and commentary by Daniel
C. Matt. Pritzker ed. v. cm.
Text includes some words in Hebrew and
Aramaic. Includes bibliographical
references. ISBN 978-0-8047-4747-9
(cloth)-- ISBN 978-0-8047-7133-7
(electronic) (vol. 1) 1. Bible. O. T.
Pentateuch Commentaries Early works to
1800. 2. Cabala-Early works to 1800. 3.
Zohar. I. Matt, Daniel Chanan. II. Title.
BM525. A52 M37 2003 296.
1 62 dc22 2003014884 To Margot Academic
Committee for the Translation of the Zohar
Daniel Abrams Bar-Ilan University Joseph
Dan Hebrew University Rachel Elior Hebrew
University Asi Farber-Ginat University of
Haifa Michael Fishbane University of
Chicago Pinchas Giller University of
Judaism Amos Goldreich Tel Aviv University
Moshe Hallamish Bar-Ilan University Melila
Hellner-Eshed Hebrew University Boaz Huss
Ben-Gurion University Moshe Idel Hebrew
University Esther Liebes Gershom Scholem
Collection
Jewish National and University Library
Yehuda Liebes Hebrew University Bernard
McGinn University of Chicago Ronit Meroz
Tel Aviv University Charles Mopsik
Centre National de la Recherche
Scientifique Michal Oron Tel Aviv
University aviva Pedaya Ben-Gurion
University Bracha Sack Ben-Gurion
University Elliot R.
Wolfson New York University Arthur Green
Co-Chair Brandeis University Rabbi Yehiel
Poupko Co-Chair Jewish Federation of
Chicago Margot Pritzker Chair, Zohar
Education Project, Inc. Daniel C.
Matt Translator, Zohar Education Project,
Inc. Contents Diagram of the Ten Sefirot
Foreword MARGOT PRITZKER Translator s
Introduction DANIEL C.
MATT Acknowledgments Introduction ARTHUR
GREEN Haqdamat Sefer ha-Zohar Parashat
Be-Reshit (Genesis 1: 1 6: 8) Parashat Noa
(Genesis 6: 9 11: 32) Abbreviations
Transliteration of Hebrew and Aramaic
Glossary Bibliography Index of Sources
Foreword
I began to study the Torah. As my facility
with the text grew, I pursued SOME YEARS
AGO the midrashic literature of the
rabbis, and the interpretations of the
classic medieval commentators.
Eventually, I began to inquire about
mystical commentaries on the Torah. I
turned to the Zohar, seeking an English
translation of its original Aramaic.
I soon learned that previous translations
not only were incomplete but also had been
undertaken in the early twentieth century.
Therefore, they did not reflect the
enormous advances in scholarship since
made by Gershom Scholem and his students.
It was at this point that I realized how
much I wanted to be able to study the
Zohar from an English translation that
would draw upon the research and
scholarship of the past half-century.
I determined to sponsor such a
translation; the book you hold in your
hands is the result. By its nature and
purpose, the Zohar is difficult to
penetrate.
For hundreds of years it was inaccessible
to all but a few.
Furthermore, after the Sabbatean episode
of the seventeenth century, the Jewish
community became concerned about the
potency of mystical ideas; leaders were
anything but eager to promulgate the
Zohar.
Even with the rise of Hasidism as a
mystically based movement starting in the
eighteenth century, the Zohar remained a
closed book.
Consequently, bringing the Zohar to the
English-reading public was and continues
to be a complex, challenging task. The
words that can express my appreciation to
Daniel C.
Matt are found on every page of his
translation of the Zohar. His scholarship,
his artistry, and his poetry speak for
themselves. You, the reader, are in his
debt.
The odyssey of the past nine years, which
will continue for some years to come, has
been shepherded through a tangle of legal
and administrative steps with the able and
devoted skill of Glen Miller.
Professor Arthur Green, who co-chairs the
Academic Committee for the Translation of
the Zohar, has been a thoughtful and
faithful counselor from the inception of
the project.
My husband Tom, while not a student of the
Zohar, recognized the magnitude and the
importance of this project.
He has kept us ever vigilant and focused
with his insightful questions and thoughts
and his constant support.
From conception through gestation and
finally to birth, this project would not
have been realized without the wisdom,
knowledge, and nurturing of Rabbi Yehiel
Poupko.
He is my teacher and my friend, and it is
to him that this edition of the Zohar is
dedicated.
It is with a sense of fulfillment and awe
for Daniel Matt s remarkable
accomplishment that my family and I now
present the Zohar to the English- reading
public
with the hope that the radiance that flows
from this great work and from the Jewish
mystical tradition will bring light to
those who seek it. Margot Pritzker
Translator s Introduction DANIEL C.
MATT (The Book of Radiance)1 has amazed
and overwhelmed readers ever SEFER
HA-ZOHAR since it emerged mysteriously in
medieval Spain (Castile) toward the end of
the thirteenth century.
Written mostly in a unique Aramaic, this
masterpiece of Kabbalah exceeds the
dimensions of a normal book; it is
virtually a body of literature, comprising
over twenty discrete sections.
The bulk of the Zohar consists of a
running commentary on the Torah, from
Genesis through Deuteronomy.
This translation begins and focuses there
in what are projected to be ten volumes;
two subsequent volumes will cover other,
shorter sections.
2 Arthur Green s introduction to this
volume traces the development of Kabbalah
and discusses the historical and literary
context of the Zohar its style the complex
question of authorship
and the symbolism of the ten sefirot
(various aspects of the divine Self). Here
I wish to treat several topics directly
related to this translation and
commentary.
Establishing the Text of the Zohar This
edition reflects a newly constructed,
precise text of the Zohar, based on
original manuscripts. Why was the creation
of such a text necessary?
All previous translations of the Zohar are
based on the standard printed editions
which nearly all derive from the Mantua
edition (1558 60)
supplemented by variant readings from the
Cremona edition (1559 60).
At first I intended to follow the same
procedure but upon examining many of the
original manuscripts of the Zohar dating
from the fourteenth through sixteenth
centuries
I discovered a significant number of
superior readings that had been rejected
or revised by editors of the first printed
editions.
Upon further examination, I noticed
something more intriguing a phenomenon
familiar to scholars of medieval texts.
Within the manuscripts themselves were
signs of an editorial process: revision,
reformulation, and emendation.
3 After careful analysis, I concluded that
certain manuscripts of older lineage
reflect an earlier version of the Zohar,
which was then reworked in manuscripts of
later lineage.
4 I realized that I could no longer rely
on the printed editions of the Zohar,
since these obscured earlier versions.
So I took it upon myself to reconstruct a
new-ancient version of the Aramaic text
based on the manuscripts, one which could
serve as the foundation for this
translation.
If I could have located a complete,
reliable manuscript of the Zohar, this
would have provided a starting point.
Unfortunately no such manuscript exists
anywhere in the world; in all likelihood
it never did, since from the start the
Zohar was circulated in sections or
booklets.
Probably no single complete Book of the
Zohar existed until it was printed nearly
three hundred years later in the sixteenth
century, collated from various
manuscripts.
5 This situation left me with two choices.
I could select the best manuscript for
each individual Torah portion of the Zohar
and produce a diplomatic text, an exact
reproduction of the original.
Or, I could fashion a critical text,
selecting from a wide range of variants in
different manuscripts.
After consulting with members of our
Academic Committee for the Translation of
the Zohar, I chose to compose a critical
text, based on a selection and evaluation
of the manuscript readings.
The primary reason was simply that even
for individual sections of the Zohar there
is no one best manuscript: each has its
own deficiencies and scribal errors.
Back in the sixteenth century, the editors
in Mantua and Cremona also fashioned
critical texts, the former drawing on ten
manuscripts, the latter on six.
6 For the first two volumes of the
translation, I identified approximately
twenty reliable manuscripts, based on the
criteria of provenance, age, lack of
scribal errors, and legibility.
The originals are preserved in the
libraries of Oxford Cambridge London Paris
Munich Rome the Vatican Parma Toronto and
the Jewish Theological Seminary
while microfilm copies are available in
the Institute for Microfilmed Hebrew
Manuscripts in the Jewish National and
University Library on the campus of the
Hebrew University Jerusalem.
7 It is appropriate to describe more fully
the methodology used in this scholarly
undertaking.
My research assistant meticulously combs
through about half of these manuscripts
and prepares a list of variant readings.
For particularly difficult words or
phrases, we check additional manuscripts.
In addition to the manuscripts my
assistant lists variants from the Mantua
and Cremona editions of the Zohar as well
as the edition used by Moses Cordovero in
his sixteenth- century commentary
Or Yaqar. 8 My procedure for establishing
the Aramaic text is as follows.
I begin with Reuven Margaliot s edition of
Sefer ha-Zohar, 9 based on the Vilna
edition, which in turn is based on the
Mantua edition. This represents a
relatively reliable starting point.
In front of me I have the list of variants
prepared by my research assistant,
photocopies of the original manuscripts,
and other witnesses referred to
previously. 10 I peruse the variants line
by line.
Some of these are simply scribal errors or
glosses, but some represent what appear to
be better readings.
When I identify an apparently better
reading, I check if it is shared and
confirmed by several reliable manuscripts
and witnesses. If it is, I consider
substituting it for the printed text.
Over the centuries Sefer ha-Zohar has been
revised by countless scribes and editors
who tried to smooth away the rough edges
of the text by adding an explanatory
phrase
correcting an apparent syntactical mistake
or taming a wild neologism by substituting
a more familiar bland term.
Often, relying on the variants, I decide
to remove these accumulated layers of
revision, thereby restoring a more
original text. I seek to recover the Zohar
s primal texture and cryptic flavor.
If the early manuscripts preserve unusual,
striking wording that is revised or
corrected by several later manuscripts and
the printed editions, I tend to go with
the older reading.
Often, according to the more reliable
manuscripts, a Zoharic rabbi creatively
paraphrases a Talmudic saying.
Some of the later manuscripts and the
printed editions may then restore this
saying to its exact Talmudic form.
In such cases I emend the printed text in
favor of the Zohar s original formulation
original in both senses: older and
creative.
In the commentary I cite the Talmudic
saying on which the paraphrase is based,
so that readers can see the transition and
trace the imaginative process.
I do not claim to be fully restoring the
original text of the Zohar. There may
never have been any such thing, since the
text probably emerged over many years,
written and distributed piecemeal.
However, through painstaking analysis of
the variants, I am able to scrape away
some seven hundred years of accretion and
corruption, and at least approach that
elusive, hypothetical original.
This Aramaic text of the Zohar, the basis
of my translation, is available for study
and scholarly examination. 11 Translation
and Commentary