All translation is inherently inadequate,
a well-intentioned betrayal.
In the words of the second-century sage
Rabbi Yehudah, One who translates a verse
literally is a liar; one who adds to it is
a blasphemer.
12 Furthermore, the Zohar is notoriously
obscure perhaps the most difficult Jewish
classic to translate. It was composed in
Castile mostly in Aramaic, a language no
longer spoken in medieval Spain.
13 The author(s) concocted a unique blend
of Aramaic out of traditional sources,
especially the Babylonian Talmud and
Targum Onqelos (an Aramaic translation of
the Torah).
This unparalleled neo-Aramaic is peppered
with enigmatic expressions, puns,
outlandish constructions, puzzling
neologisms, solecisms, and traces of
medieval Hebrew and Castilian.
The Zohar s prose is poetic, overflowing
with multiple connotations, composed in
such a way that you often cannot pin down
the precise meaning of a phrase.
The language befits the subject matter,
which is mysterious, elusive, and
ineffable; words can merely suggest and
hint.
An unfathomable process may be stated,
then immediately denied: It split and did
not split its aura.
14 Occasionally we encounter oxymorons,
such as new-ancient words, alluding to the
dual nature of the Zohar s secrets,
recently composed yet ascribed to ancient
sources.
15 The first impulse of divine emanation
is described as (botsina de-qardinuta), a
spark of impenetrable darkness, 16 so
intensely bright that it cannot be seen.
Through the centuries, the potency of the
Zohar s language has mesmerized even those
who could not plumb its secrets.
While kabbalists delved deeply, the
uninitiated chanted the lyrical Aramaic,
often unaware of its literal meaning.
In the words of an eighteenth-century
mystic, Even if one does not understand,
the language is suited to the soul.
17 No doubt it is risky to translate the
Zohar, but it would be worse to leave
these gems of wisdom buried in their
ancient Aramaic vault.
So I have plunged in, seeking to transmit
some of the Zohar s magic.
The previous English translation (composed
in the 1930s by Harry Sperling, Maurice
Simon, and Paul Levertoff) reads smoothly
but often misunderstands the text.
18 Its genteel prose is more a paraphrase
than an accurate translation avoiding
unfamiliar terms, censoring erotic
material, skipping difficult passages and
even entire sections.
The English flows too fluently compared to
the original, subduing the unruly Aramaic,
failing to render its untamed vibrancy.
Moreover, since the translation is
unaccompanied by a commentary, the
symbolism remains impenetrable. Despite
its shortcomings, I have learned much from
consulting this translation, along with
others.
19 But my approach is significantly
different. Though I wish to make the Zohar
accessible, I also want to convey its
strangeness, potency, and rich ambiguity.
Here the commentary is essential.
When the translation cannot adequately
express a multifaceted phrase, I unfold
the range of meaning in the commentary.
When the translation is as cryptic as the
original Aramaic, the commentary rescues
the stranded reader. My style of
translation is literal yet poetic.
I am convinced that a literal rendering of
the Zohar is not only the most accurate
but also the most colorful and zestful the
best way to transmit the lyrical energy of
the Aramaic.
Still, at times, the multivalent language
invites a certain freedom of expression.
Let me cite two related examples.
In Zohar 1: 83a, Rabbi Shim on describes
the nighttime journey of the soul, soaring
skyward from her sleeping body: Flying,
she encounters those (qumrin tehirin) of
defilement.
What does this bizarre term mean? The
Sperling-Simon translation renders it as
certain bright but unclean essences.
20 The English translation of Tishby s
Wisdom of the Zohar reads: the deceiving
lights of uncleanness
21 while Tishby s original Hebrew
translation reads a bit differently:
(qimmurei negohot) roughly: vaulted
splendors though in his note he
acknowledges that the meaning is doubtful.
22 I render the sentence as follows:
Flying, she encounters those hooded,
hunchbacked, dazzling demons of
defilement.
The accompanying commentary explains that
these are malevolent forces who block the
ascent of an unworthy soul.
Qumrin derives via rabbinic usage from the
Greek qamara, arched cover, while tehirin
is a cognate of the Aramaic tihara,
meaning brightness, noon. One class of
demons is named tiharei, noonday demons.
The virtuous soul who evades these demons
reaches heaven and receives a divine
message.
According to another Zoharic passage (1:
130a), while descending back to her
sleeping earthbound body, the soul is
assailed by ( avilei teriqin).
The Sperling-Simon translation renders
this phrase as malignant bands. 23 The
English translation of Tishby s Wisdom of
the Zohar reads: ill-intentioned
destructive powers.
24 I render it as ravaging bands of
truculent stingers. The commentary
explains that avilei derives from either
evel, band, group, or the verb vl, to
injure, destroy.
Teriqin derives from the root trq, to
sting, bite. Although the Zohar s basic
vocabulary is limited, its roots generate
a rich variety of meanings.
For example, the root (tqn) spans the
following range: establish, institute,
mend, restore, correct, perfect, prepare,
arrange, array, adorn.
The root (slq) can mean: rise, raise,
culminate, attain, surpass, depart,
disappear, die, remove, postpone, reserve,
emit (fragrance).
In normal Aramaic and Hebrew the specific
verbal conjugation determines which
meaning of the root applies but the Zohar
ignores or flouts rules of grammar
confusing the conjugations
playing with multiple meanings often
leaving the reader stumped and wondering.
Mysticism strives to penetrate a realm
beyond distinctions but this mystical
masterpiece demands constant decision
making
challenging the reader or translator to
navigate between conflicting meanings and
determine the appropriate one or sometimes
to discover how differing meanings pertain
simultaneously.
The frequent dilemmas of interpretation
suggest that in exploring the Zohar,
linguistic search and spiritual search go
hand in hand.
Especially puzzling, though charming, are
the neologisms strewn throughout the
Zohar, intended to bewilder and astound
the reader.
25 Some derive from rare Talmudic terms
which the author refashions by
intentionally misspelling or by inverting
letters some derive from Greek Latin or
Castilian some appear to be pure
inventions.
These nonce words often contain the
letters (tet), (samekh), (pe), (qof), and
(resh) in various combinations: (quspita),
(qatpira), (qirta), (qesira), (qustera),
(tufsera).
Qustera derives from the Latin word
castrum (plural, castra), fortress,
castle. Qatpira and its variations mean
several things, including knot (based on
Aramaic [qitra]) and waterskin.
26 One newly coined noun, (tiqla), is
particularly versatile. In various
contexts it can mean scale, hollow of the
hand, fist, potter s wheel, and water
clock.
This last sense refers to a device
described in ancient and medieval
scientific literature which in the Zohar
functions as an alarm clock
calibrated to wake kabbalists precisely at
midnight for the ritual study of Torah. 27
A similar device was employed in Christian
monasteries to rouse monks for their
vigils.
How appropriate to invent a word for an
invention!
Often by pondering the context comparing
Zoharic and rabbinic parallels and
scouring sundry dictionaries and lexicons
one can decipher or at least conjecture
the meaning of these weird terms
but some remain as perplexing as
originally intended. 28 In translating
biblical citations, I have consulted
various translations but generally
composed my own.
29 Sometimes, in quoting a verse, the
Zohar intends a meaning different from
that conveyed by any known translation.
In such cases I usually translate the
verse as the Zohar understands it and then
explain the difference in the commentary.
The main purpose of the commentary is to
clarify the dense symbolism and unique
terminology.
Here I seek to elicit the meaning of the
text, drawing it forth from the Zohar s
own language without being heavy-handed
without ruining the subtlety and ambiguity
of the original.
Remember that the Zohar was not intended
to be easily understood but rather to be
deciphered. I want to allow and compel the
reader to wrestle with the text.
Over the centuries, the tendency has grown
to overinterpret, with commentators often
insisting on assigning sefirotic
significance to nearly every image and
metaphor.
I have resisted this tendency, while still
identifying sefirotic correspondences when
they are called for.
Often a phrase or passage implies more
than one meaning; the reader is encouraged
to ponder various possibilities.
To clarify the context, I cite sources and
parallels from the Bible, rabbinic
literature, and the Zohar itself, with
occasional references to secondary
literature.
The aim is not to overwhelm the reader by
citing everything conceivable, but rather
to provide what is needed to make sense of
this enigmatic work of art.
30 In composing the commentary I have
drawn on numerous traditional and modern
Zohar commentaries especially those of
Moses Cordovero Shim on Lavi ayyim Vital
Abraham Galante Shalom Buzaglo
Yehudah Ashlag Charles Mopsik and Daniel
Frisch.
31 Other valuable resources include the
annotations of Reuven Margaliot (Nitsotsei
Zohar) in his edition of the Zohar Isaiah
Tishby s monumental Mishnat ha-Zohar (The
Wisdom of the Zohar)
Gershom Scholem s Annotated Zohar and
Yehuda Liebes s eye-opening Peraqim
be-Millon Sefer ha-Zohar (Sections of the
Zohar Lexicon).
A glossary, bibliography, and an index of
biblical and rabbinic citations are
appended to each volume. A diagram of the
ten sefirot appears on page xi of this
volume.
The standard Aramaic pagination of the
Zohar is indicated in the running head on
each page (e. g. , 1: 34b).
How to Read the Zohar There is no single
right way to read and proceed through the
Zohar, but I can point out certain
features and suggest several guidelines.
First of all, the Zohar is dynamic full of
surprises.
Typically we find that Rabbi iyya and
Rabbi Yose were walking on the way
wandering through the hills of Galilee
sharing secrets of Torah but also moving
from one dimension to another
accompanied by Shekhinah the Divine
Presence Herself. Who knows whom they will
encounter on the road?
A child amazes them with wisdom, a beggar
enriches them with precious teachings, a
cantankerous old donkey-driver turns out
to be a sage in disguise. You are about to
enter an enchanted realm.
Still, although the Zohar sometimes reads
like a mystical novel, remember that this
is fundamentally a biblical commentary.
It s helpful to have a Bible at hand to
check the original context, to see how a
particular verse becomes a springboard for
the imagination.
Every few pages we read: Rabbi iyya opened
Rabbi Yose opened signifying that he is
opening not only his exposition but also
the verse: disclosing new layers of
meaning
expanding the range of interpretation. The
reader of the Zohar should be open, too
open to new ways of thinking and
imagining. As the avrayya (Companions)
continually exclaim, Come and see!
The Zohar is firmly rooted in tradition
but thrives on discovery. This verse has
been discussed, but come and see! This
verse has been established, but come and
see!
32 Innovations of Torah are required here!
33 Innovation emerges through scrutinizing
the biblical text, so questioning becomes
a supreme value.
After Rabbi izkiyah asks Rabbi Abba a
challenging question, we are told that
Rabbi Abba came and kissed him. 34 Why?
Because, as one commentator notes here,
The question is half the answer; without a
question, there is no reason for an
answer.
35 Even when the meaning of a verse is
perfectly clear, the Zohar may question
its structure, sometimes probing so deeply
that the reader is stunned.
To take an extreme example, come and see
how Rabbi El azar deals with the
concluding verse in the story of the
Garden of Eden, which could hardly be more
explicit: He drove out Adam.
36 We do not know who divorced whom: if
the blessed Holy One divorced Adam, or
not.
37 As the rabbi demonstrates by exegetical
artifice the mystical meaning is the
shocking alternative lurking within that
bland phrase or not : Adam drove out
divorced Shekhinah
splitting Her from Her divine partner Tif
eret and from himself. Once, as Adam,
humanity was wedded to God.
The original sin lies in losing intimacy
with the divine, thereby constricting
unbounded awareness.
This loss follows inevitably from tasting
the fruit of discursive knowledge; it is
the price we pay for maturity and culture.
The spiritual challenge is to search for
that lost treasure without renouncing the
self or the world.
As you read, see how the avrayya coax new
meaning out of a biblical verse, phrase,
word or even letter.
Often they rely on standard rabbinic
techniques of interpretation such as
verbal analogy: Here is written:
[such-and-such a biblical expression]
and there is written: [an identical (or
nearly identical) expression] implying a
close link between the two expressions.
The hermeneutical leap may be long, far
from the literal meaning, but sometimes a
verse is read hyperliterally, ignoring
idiomatic usage in favor of a radically
spiritual sense.
For example, when God commands Abraham,
(Lekh lekha), Go forth, ...
to the land that I will show you (Genesis
12: 1), Rabbi El azar insists on reading
the words more literally than they were
intended: Lekh lekha, Go to yourself!
38 Search deep within to discover your
true self. Another startling illustration
is the Zohar s reading of the opening
words of the Torah, traditionally
rendered: In the beginning God created.
Everyone assumes the verse describes the
creation of the world, but for the Zohar
it alludes to a more primal beginning: the
emanation of the sefirot from Ein Sof (
Infinity ).
How is this allusion discovered, or
invented?
By insisting on reading the Hebrew words
in their precise order: (Bereshit bara
Elohim) construed now as With beginning It
created Elohim that is by means of okhmah
(the sefirah of Wisdom
known as beginning) It (ineffable Ein Sof)
emanated Binah (the sefirah of
Understanding known by the divine name
Elohim). 39 God, it turns out, is the
object of the verse, not the subject!
The ultimate divine reality, Ein Sof,
transcends and explodes our comfortable
conception of God.
The Zohar dares us to confront this
reality, as it transforms the familiar
story of Creation into divine biography.
So, as you undertake this adventure,
expect to be surprised stay alert.
The Zohar s teachings are profound and
intense; one who hopes to enter and emerge
in peace should be careful, persevering,
simultaneously receptive and active.
The message is not served to you on a
platter; you must engage the text and join
the search for meaning. Follow the words
to what lies beyond and within; open the
gates of imagination.
Above all, don t reduce everything you
encounter in these pages to something you
already know. Beware of trying to find the
essence of a particular teaching.
Although usually essence is the goal of
mystical search, here essence is
inadequate unless it stimulates you to
explore ever deeper layers, to question
your assumptions about tradition, God, and
self.
In the words of a Zoharic parable: There
was a man who lived in the mountains. He
knew nothing about those who lived in the
city. He sowed wheat and ate the kernels
raw. One day he entered the city.
They offered him good bread. The man
asked, What s this for? They replied, It s
bread, to eat! He ate, and it tasted very
good. He asked, What s it made of? They
answered, Wheat.
Later they offered him thick loaves
kneaded with oil. He tasted them, and
asked, And what are these made of? They
answered, Wheat. Later they offered him
royal pastry kneaded with honey and oil.
He asked, And what are these made of? They
answered, Wheat. He said, Surely I am the
master of all of these, since I eat the
essence of all of these: wheat!
Because of that view, he knew nothing of
the delights of the world, which were lost
on him.
So it is with one who grasps the principle
but is unaware of all those delectable
delights deriving, diverging from that
principle.
40 Acknowledgments the people who have
helped me begin to plumb the Zohar would
burst TO THANK ALL this book s binding.
So here I will briefly trace my path and
acknowledge some of those who have helped
me along the way.
My father, of blessed memory, Rabbi
Hershel Jonah Matt, taught me that God is
real, and that by studying Torah you can
experience Shekhinah, the Divine Presence.
(I have sketched his life and assembled
his writings in Walking Humbly with God. )
My mother, Gustine, has always been a
fountain of love and a source of strength;
I am grateful for her deep wisdom.
I first ventured into Sefer ha-Zohar in
1970 during my junior year abroad at
Hebrew University in Jerusalem.
The thick volumes were simultaneously
forbidding and alluring; deciphering the
Aramaic text was a puzzle, a challenge, a
quest.
Soon I fell in love with the Zohar,
captivated by its lush imagery and poetic
magic.
My teachers that year in Kabbalah included
Joseph Dan, Efraim Gottlieb, and Rivka
Schatz-Uffenheimer and a kabbalist, Rav
Toledano. I thank them all for guiding me
into the orchard.
From Jerusalem I returned to Brandeis
University where I completed my
undergraduate degree and then after some
European travel plunged into graduate
study in Jewish mysticism with Alexander
Altmann
a superb Wissenschaft scholar and a gem of
a man.
He directed my doctoral dissertation which
consisted of a critical edition of The
Book of Mirrors a previously unpublished
fourteenth-century Hebrew commentary on
the Torah by David ben Judah he- asid.
I chose to edit this text because it
included the first extended translations
of the Zohar, from Aramaic to Hebrew.
I was encouraged to undertake this project
by Gershom Scholem, while serving as his
teaching assistant in the fall of 1975.
After I completed my dissertation my
friend Arthur Green invited me to compose
an annotated translation of selections
from the Zohar for the Paulist Press
as one volume in their Classics of Western
Spirituality. Years earlier, Art had
initiated me into the mystical thought of
Hasidism, which stimulated me to uncover
its roots in the Zohar.
I am grateful for his insight and guidance
over the years, and for demonstrating how
to combine scholarship and spirituality.
For two decades, I taught Jewish mysticism
in Berkeley at the Graduate Theological
Union (GTU), a school where Jews,
Christians, and Buddhists study side by
side, stimulating one another.
I learned much there from my colleagues
and students; I want to thank, in
particular, David Winston and David Biale
for their friendship and for the depth of
their learning.
I had been at the GTU for many years
already when, one afternoon in September
1995, Art Green called me on the phone and
told me about a woman from Chicago named
Margot Pritzker.
She had been studying the Zohar with Rabbi
Yehiel Poupko, but the dated English
translation they were reading had proved
inadequate.
Margot had decided to commission a new
translation, said Art, and she was
inviting me to undertake the task! I was
astounded, and told my friend that I
needed a few days to consider this.
The days turned into weeks, which turned
into months, as I kept wrestling with the
thrilling, terrifying offer.
I decided to translate a short section of
the Zohar to see how it felt, but I poured
myself into the experiment so intensely,
day after day, that I was left drained,
exhausted, discouraged.
How could I keep this up for years and
years?
I reluctantly resolved to decline the
offer, but Art convinced me to at least
meet this woman and her rabbi; so the
following May, the four of us gathered at
the O Hare Hyatt.
I expressed my hesitation to them, and
told Margot that the project could take
twelve to fifteen years to which she
responded, You re not scaring me!
I was won over by her genuine desire to
penetrate the Zohar and make it accessible
to English readers.
A year or so later, over Independence Day
weekend 1997, the Zohar project formally
began with a two-day conference outside
Chicago attended by the leading academic
scholars of Kabbalah.
They were invited not just to participate
in this conference but to constitute the
Academic Committee for the Translation of
the Zohar, which was intended to guide and
support this translation.
(The members of the committee are listed
at the front of this volume. ) Over the
past six years, I have benefited immensely
from their feedback and encouragement.
I thank all of them, especially Moshe
Idel, Yehuda Liebes, Ronit Meroz, and
Elliot Wolfson. Time and again, Yehuda
generously shared insights drawn from his
vast, intimate knowledge of the Zohar.
I smile, recalling the many times we
wrestled over the mystifying Aramaic,
deepening our understanding of the text
and our friendship.
I spent the second year of the project
(1998 99) at the Institute for Advanced
Studies at the Hebrew University of
Jerusalem on a program entitled Studying
the Zohar, directed by Yehuda Liebes.
Here seven fellows and seven other
visiting scholars (all fourteen of us,
members of the Academic Committee) engaged
in research on various aspects of the
text.
Our weekly seminars were devoted to a
close reading of Zohar passages often
those that I was currently translating.
Here I presented a draft of my translation
and benefited from the responses of my
colleagues.
I am grateful to all of them, as well as
to the staff of the Institute, who
provided an ideal setting for our
research.
When the yearlong program ended in June
1999, the institute graciously allowed me
to retain an office for the following year
as well.
In the summer of 2000, it was finally time
to leave the tranquil environment of the
institute.
Fortunately Rabbi David Hartman provided
me with an office at the Shalom Hartman
Institute across town
where I spent the following two years
(2000 2002) in an atmosphere
simultaneously peaceful and stimulating.
David s enthusiasm for Torah energizes
everyone around him, and I thank him for
his support and encouragement, and for his
healthy skepticism of mystical excess.
I was enriched by my contact with many of
the fellows at the Hartman Institute
especially Donniel Hartman (co-director)
Daniel Abrams Moshe Halbertal Moshe Idel
Israel Knohl Levi Lauer
Menachem Lorberbaum Yair Lorberbaum Israel
Ta-Shma and Shlomo Naeh. Shlomo was always
generous in sharing with me his immense
linguistic knowledge.
As described in the Translator s
Introduction I have based my English
rendering on a critical text of the Zohar
which I have constructed by drawing on
variant readings from a wide range of
manuscripts.
I could not have accomplished this task
without my indefatigable research
assistant Barry Mark
who spent more than five years
painstakingly preparing lists of these
variants for the first two volumes of the
translation. I thank him immensely for his
years of devotion to this task.
Recently, Merav Carmeli has followed in
his footsteps, proving herself a worthy
successor, and I am indebted to her as
well.
Arthur Green has carefully read large
portions of this translation and offered
criticism and suggestions, for which I am
truly grateful.
As co-chair of the Academic Committee for
the Translation of the Zohar, he has
helped guide the project from its birth.
Numerous libraries offered valuable
resources especially the Gershom Scholem
Collection and the Institute of
Microfilmed Hebrew Manuscripts both housed
in the Jewish National and University
Library
Jerusalem.
I want to thank in particular Esther
Liebes (head of the Scholem Collection)
for her constant willingness to help
Benjamin Richler (director of the
Institute of Microfilmed Hebrew
Manuscripts) along with his staff and Adam
Verete for checking obscure references.
Other libraries and collections that
provided precious material include:
Bayerische Staatsbibliothek Munich
Biblioteca Apostolica Vatican Biblioteca
Casanatense Rome Biblioteca Palatina Parma
Biblioth que nationale Paris the Bodleian
Library University of Oxford the British
Library Cambridge University Library the
Flora Lamson Hewlett Library of the
Graduate Theological Union
the Friedberg Collection University of
Toronto Library the Guenzburg Collection
of the Russian State Library Moscow and
the Library of the Jewish Theological
Seminary.
The team at Stanford University Press, led
by Geoffrey Burn and Norris Pope, has been
superb to work with and wondrously adept
at generating the first, demanding volumes
of this complex classic.
In addition to Geoffrey and Norris, I want
to thank Lowell Britson, Alan Harvey,
Randy Hurst, David Jackson, Patricia
Myers, and especially Mariana Raykov and
Rob Ehle. Rabbi David E. S.
Stein s expert copyediting polished this
Book of Radiance.
As I toiled and exulted over the Zohar I
have received sound advice and warm
encouragement from my far-flung siblings:
Rabbi Jonathan Matt (Israel) David Matt
(Iowa) and Debbie Erdfarb (New Jersey).
My wife, ana, and I have been delving
together into the Zohar ever since we met,
discovering and sharing its new-ancient
meanings, gazing into each other s souls
through its penetrating lens.
Thank you for your compassionate wisdom
and unfailing support. You bring to life
the verse: On her tongue, a Torah of love
(Proverbs 31: 26).
You help me understand the words of Rabbi
El azar (Zohar 1: 141a): Isaac embraced
faith, seeing Shekhinah dwelling in his
wife.
My angelic children, Michaella and
Gavriel, have never lost their sense of
wonder, and I thank them for arousing
mine. May this translation touch you and
open up new worlds!
Rabbi Yehiel Poupko, co-chair of the
Academic Committee, has excited and
inspired me ever since our first meeting
seven years ago.
Descended from a famous kabbalist, the
Shelah (Isaiah Horowitz), he is intimately
bound to the Zohar and has devoted himself
to spreading its light.
I thank him for conducting this project so
deftly and passionately. Glen Miller, vice
president of Zohar Education Project, Inc.
, has vitalized this adventure through his
vision and devotion.
On a practical level, he has navigated the
ark of Zohar through countless legal and
administrative passageways. I am
profoundly grateful. Thomas J.
Pritzker has generously supported and
heartened all of us through this long
process. I thank him deeply.
And I wonder: Is there a correlation
between Tom s passion for exploring caves
to discover ancient Asian art and the fact
that according to tradition (see below
page 76)
the Zohar was composed in a cave? Margot,
how can I express my gratitude to you? You
have enabled me to devote myself to what I
love that is every scholar s dream.
You have not only sponsored this immense
project; you have participated, probing
the translation and commentary, skillfully
guiding the entire process.
I hope that I have responded to your bold
generosity by opening up the Zohar for you
and for all those who, thanks to you, will
be illumined by its rays. To you I
dedicate this translation.
Finally, to the One beyond all names:
Blessed are You for enlivening and
sustaining me, and for bringing me to this
moment. D. C. M.
Introduction ARTHUR GREEN I is the great
medieval Jewish compendium of mysticism,
myth, and esoteric THE ZOHAR teaching.
It may be considered the highest
expression of Jewish literary imagination
in the Middle Ages. Surely it is one of
the most important bodies of religious
text of all times and places.
It is also a lush garden of sacred eros
filled to overflowing with luxurious
plantings of love between master and
disciples among the mystical companions
themselves
between the souls of Israel and Shekhinah
God s lovely bride but most of all between
the male and female elements that together
make up the Godhead.
Revered and canonized by generations of
faithful devotees the Zohar s secret
universe serves as the basis of
kabbalistic faith both within the
boundaries of Judaism and beyond it down
to our own day
which has seen a significant revival of
interest in Kabbalah and its teachings.
The Zohar is a work of sacred fantasy.
To say this about it is by no means to
impugn the truth of its insights or the
religious profundity of its teachings. The
Middle Ages are filled with fantasy.
Angels and demons heavenly principalities
chambers of heaven and rungs within the
soul secret treasures of the spirit that
could be seen only by the elect
esoteric domains without end all of these
were to be found in the writings of Jewish
Christian and Islamic authors throughout
medieval times. All of them partake of
fantasy.
It may be said that all theological
elaborations, insofar as they are allowed
to become pictorial, are fantasy.
They depict realities that have not been
seen except by the inner eye of those who
describe them, or by their sacred sources.
In the case of Judaism, prohibitions
derived from the second of the Ten
Commandments forbade the depiction of such
sacred realms in any medium other than
that of words.
Perhaps because of this, the literary
imagination became extraordinarily rich.
All those creative energies that might in
other contexts have sought to reify sacred
myth in painting sculpture manuscript
illumination
or stained glass here had to focus on the
word especially on the timeless Jewish
project of commentary and exegesis.
In this sense the Zohar may be seen as the
greatest work of medieval Jewish
iconography one that exists only in the
words of the written page
thence to be distilled in the imagination
of its devoted students. Written in a
lofty combination of Aramaic and Hebrew,
the Zohar was first revealed to the world
around the year 1300.
Those who distributed it orally and in
small written fragments claimed that it
was an ancient text they had recently
rediscovered
and that it had been composed in the
circle of those described within its pages
Rabbi Shim on son of Yo ai and his
disciples who lived in the land of Israel
during the second century of the Common
Era.
The obscurity of the Zohar s origins
combined with its unique language and its
rich poetic imagination to lend to the
work an aura of unfathomable mystery.
While a few of the more critical spirits
in each century doubted the Zohar and
questioned its authority the great
majority of readers and later of Jewry as
a whole
believed in the Zohar and venerated it
considering it a holy revelation and a
sacred scripture that was to be ranked
alongside the Bible and the Talmud as a
divinely inspired source of religious
truth.
Only in modern times, and largely for
apologetic reasons, was the Zohar deleted
from the canon of what was considered
mainstream Judaism.
Translation of the Zohar into Western
languages began as early as the fifteenth
century, when passages were rendered into
Latin for use by Christian devotees of
esoteric lore in Renaissance Italy.
In the twentieth century, various
translations of the Zohar, or at least of
most sections of it, appeared in German,
French, and English.
The previous standard English translation
is that of Harry Sperling and Maurice
Simon, published in 1931 34 by the Soncino
Press.
The present translation and commentary by
Daniel Matt reflect the high standards of
Zohar scholarship that have been achieved
in recent decades.
These are the result of the new attention
paid to Kabbalah in academic circles
largely thanks to the writings of Gershom
Scholem (1897 1982) and the cadre of
scholars he and his successors have
trained within the Israeli universities.
The first to bring Scholem s approach to
kabbalistic studies to North American
shores was Alexander Altmann (1906 1987)
at Brandeis University
whose students include both the translator
of these volumes and the author of this
introduction.
Further discussion of the translation and
the principles underlying it may be found
in the Translator s Introduction.
The purpose of this introduction is to
equip the reader to better appreciate the
Zohar text.
The translation before you is one that
takes full cognizance of the poetic spirit
in which the Zohar was composed and
especially of the elevated tone achieved
by its unique use of language.
To appreciate these in the fullest sense,
it must be said, the Zohar needs to be
read, indeed studied, in the original.
Like most of the kabbalistic tradition
within which it stands, the Zohar is
entranced with the mysteries of language,
in both its oral and written forms.
No translation could do justice to the
Zohar s rich and creative appropriation of
the nuances of Hebrew and Aramaic speech
its startling transformation of countless
biblical verses
and the frequent subtle rereadings of the
Talmudic/midrashic legacy that together
comprise much of the Zohar s charm and
genius.
Nevertheless, a great deal can be gained
through carefully reading and studying the
Zohar in translation.
For this to be possible, however, the
reader needs to be initiated into the
symbolic language in which the work was
written.
1 Although the Zohar s poesis often
transcends the symbolic conventions, they
are always present in the background of
the writers imagination.
So too, it was assumed, would they be
present in the mind of the reader.
The Zohar was composed in the hope that it
would be passed on and studied within
circles of initiates, as indeed it was for
many generations.
To appreciate the Zohar, you will also
need to know something of the historical
and literary context in which it appeared.
The Zohar made use of a very wide
selection of Jewish texts that preceded it
ranging from the Torah itself to legal
mystical
and philosophical works that were written
just shortly before its appearance.
It reflected on all of these and used them
freely as inspiration for its own unique
sort of innovative and sometimes even
playful religious creativity.
It is also much concerned with the Jews
and their history: that recorded in
Scripture, the present exile, and the
dream of messianic redemption.
These, too, form part of the background
needed to understand the Zohar.
This introduction will begin by outlining
the development of Kabbalah in the century
leading up to the Zohar, considering also
the use made in Kabbalah of prior Jewish
sources.
We will then turn to the Zohar itself,
discussing in turn its style of thought
and exegesis, its narrative modes, and the
question of the Zohar s appearance and
authorship.
Because this essay serves as an
introduction to the entire Zohar text, we
will not quote passages to exemplify the
analysis offered.
We hope that the reader will proceed from
this introduction to a careful reading of
the text and commentary
finding ample passages throughout the
Zohar against which to test the claims
offered in this brief introductory essay.
The tall order detailed in the preceding
paragraphs requires a disclaimer.
Monographs and learned articles have been
written on each of the subjects just
mentioned. Some of them have been the
subject of entire books. This